Kenneth Miralles Mora

People Manager, Innovator

Contact

Address

Zapote, Quesada Duaran San José, SJ, 10801

Phone

882 364 68

E-mail

k_miralles@hotmail.com

LinkedIn

https://www.linkedin.com/in/kennethmiralles-mba-8

English

Skills	
Process improvement	
Coaching and mentoring	Excellent
Efficient multi-tasker	Excellent
Effective leader	Excellent
Innovation	Excellent
	Excellent
Operations management	Excellent
Software	
MS Office 365	
MS Project	Excellent
AutoCAD	Excellent
Dreamweaver & Flash	Very Good
	Very Good
Tableau & Power Bl	Medium
Languages	
Spanish	

Customer-oriented People Manager with 20 years of experience focused on increasing Productivity, Value-Added, and Innovation. Adaptive and deadline-oriented with the capacity to execute and complete multiple projects in high-stress environments. Meticulous leader and strategic planner with comprehensive managerial acumen, offering excellent Leadership.

Work History

2018-02-2020-07

Operations Manager - Metcal Engineering Services, Curridabat, Costa Rica

Metcal is a Calibration Services company and Measurement Equipment provider that is compliant with ISO17025, serving most of the Multinational Healthcare, Electronic, and Aviation manufacturing and services companies in Costa Rica. Strict compliance with ISO13485 standards. The calibration is a critical service meaning that there is a high risk if it is not done right or if it takes too much time to get the calibration certificated. Among the services provided outside calibration are maintenance and software validation.

The main technologies delivered by Metcal are:

- Vision CMM
- Torque and Force Gauges •
- Measurement Equipment

Achievements: This was a fixed-term position that got extended from 12 to 30 months. Manage a project to improve productivity by reducing deliverable times by 50% and increasing productivity by 50%. Migrate the quality system to the new ISO 17025:2017. Increase sales by at least 100%. Improve overall finance and debt numbers. Improve same-day certificate deliverable and customer service culture with the mindset that we are as good as our last service. A day without a manufacturing line producing parts could mean a loss of \$50K in production and \$5K to \$15K lost in costs. So calibration is a critical service.

2015-06 -2018-01

IT Manager - Lizzy Castro Real Estate Solutions, San Jose, Costa Rica

A new real estate company in Costa Rica, that achieve a portfolio of properties worth more than \$100 Million in the first year. A website with a new look and feel in the country that matches the best real estate websites around the world.

Achievements: Develop a Web site in WordPress, setup Insightly as the customer relationship management (CRM) software, and manage all Digital Marketing campaigns including Google, Facebook, and Google Ads. Automated posts and crossposting between channels like youtube, Twitter, and Facebook.

2014-03 -2015-05

Business Development Manager - UST Global, Escazu, Costa Rica

UST's initial plan was to open an operation with 250 engineers for which I was going to be the delivery director, but the plan changed to look for local deals in Costa Rica. UST is an IT integrator for SAP, Oracle, IBM, Salesforce, Microsoft, Pegasystems, Peoplesoft, with engineering capabilities in ASIC development, software development, mobile development, and as a source for contingency workforce.

For the technologies used, UST is a 1 stop IT and Services company and UST covers all areas of IT, for instance with CCSS I work on consulting for a BYOD which was an MDM and MBaaS solution using AirWatch and FeedHenry. Mobile design prototypes using In Vision for BCR, MIDEPLAN.

Achievements: Opened business cases and solutions for Banco de Costa Rica, Coopeservidores, Walmart, Intel, BCR, CCSS, MOPT, MIDEPLAN, Teradyne, Panduit among others. The business models included: SaaS, PaaS, laaS, BOT, Fixed Price. Solutions included a Smart City Solution for Electronic payment and operations of buses, Mobile apps for healthcare and banking, Salesforce Implementation, BMP, Analytics, Call Center BOT among others. Work on building the image of UST in Costa Rica. The first employee in Costa Rica.

2008-03 -2014-03

Native

Native/Professional

Quality Manager - HPE Network R&D, Heredia, Costa Rica

HPE Networking oversaw the development of architecture and functionality of new ASICs for Networking, embedded software for mobile networks, and automated testing of new software releases

The technologies used by HPE were:

- ASIC development tools and best practices
- Java, Python, Pearl, and Tcl/Tk
- CCNA switching and Security

Achievements: Managed several projects like +\$1.2 Government funds for training +100 engineers in new tech, New GUI development for the automation framework to enable network engineers with no programming skills to use the framework. Project Manage Regression, Stress, Security, and Conformance Testing for all new products and releases. Developed new tech leads and new managers. Project management of the startup and the quality programs for new products. Improving processes and methods to reduce time to market by automating testing at different levels of the process and using the 20-80 rule. Work with teams in Canada, the USA, India, and Costa Rica. Managed projects using Scrum and Waterfall.

Certifications

Agile-Lean Methods Scrum & Kanban

Completed 2020

Artificial Intelligence

Completed 2020

Data Science

Completed 2021

Python Development

Completed 2021

Education

MBA MARKETING

ULACIT San José Magna Cum Laude 2008-10 to 2011-03

MBA FINANCE

ULACIT San José Magna Cum Laude 2009-01 to 2011-06

MSc. ARTIFICIAL INTELLIGENCE

TEC Cartago Thesis Pending – 95% GPA 1995-10 to 1999-07

Bachelor. ELECTRONIC ENGINEERING

TEC Cartago 1990-01 to 1995-06

Citizenships

COSTA RICA

SPAIN

Social

LINKEDIN

GitHub for Job Search

GITHUI

LinkedIn Profile

Data Science & Al

LIBRARIES & APIs

Apache Spark, Json, requests, urllib, BeautifulSoup, NumPy, Pandas, Scikitlearn, SciPy, ipython-sql, Apache Zeppelin, Matplotlib, Seaborn, OpenCV, Folium, Geopy, Pillow, Tesseract, Kraken, Watson Studio API, Discovery API, Speech to Text API, Text to Speech API, Chatbot API, Vison Recognition API, Facebook API, Slack API, Foursquare API, IBM Cloud, Anaconda

2001-02 - Operations Manager - X-TEL Communications, San Jose, Costa Rica

X-Tel was a top drive test tool provider for measure and troubleshoot cellular networks in real-time in the USA for TDMA, GSM, CDMA, WCDMA, and LTE

The technologies used by X-TEL were:

- Delphi, Java, .NET, C++, PHP, MySQL
- 2G, 3G, and LTE Cellular protocols
- Autonomous, Remote, and Cloud Analytics

<u>Achievements:</u> First company to have multiple phone support in the same computer, a mobile app, autonomous testing, and data cloud analytics. Company setup and management. Sales to AT&T, Cingular, T-Mobile, America Mobile, TIM in the USA, Latin America, and EU. In charge of the startup. Project Management of Software Development, Continuous Integration, and Testing.

1999-08 - **Project Engineer** - RemecWireless, San Diego, USA 2001-01

Remec Wireless manufactured Microware filters for Mobile Phone carriers, these filters are mounted on each tower and there are filters for receiving and transmitting. These filters were made using CCN and CMM machines. Each filter had RF ports to sense power using coupling technology. The development of the filters is not an exact science, so the design must be improved for mass production. This was a New Product Development position for manufacturing, validation, min waste, and max productivity.

The technologies used by REMEC were:

- CNN and CMM technologies
- AutoCAD Design
- Automated Test Equipment (ATE)
- .NET Software Testing using IEEE488 port interface
- Vector Network Analyzers (VNN)
- Noise Figure, Spectrum Analyzer, Power Meters
- Capacitance material testing

<u>Achievements</u>: Project Management for 3 New Product Introduction Projects (NPI) from San Diego to CR, Automated Test Equipment (ATE) test time improvement, design of new ATE for new products, and product improvement for high volume manufacturing. Got an offer for an H1B Visa support due to the impact of my job at the bottom line and time to market.

1999-01 - **Software Quality Engineer** - Baxter Healthcare, Cartago, Costa Rica

Baxter IV Systems manufactured healthcare devices for blood and medicine administration to patients. Baxter was the first ISO 18000 certified company in Costa Rica, run Six-Sigma processes, and had the first black belt certified engineers in Costa Rica, it was the pioneer in healthcare manufacturing in Costa Rica.

The technologies implemented in Costa Rica were:

- Plastic tube extruders
- Plastic molding components
- PLC part assembly
- Software Validation
- Digital Signature for documents
- Wi-Fi data collecting and label printing inline

<u>Achievements</u>: Software Validation Protocols (SVPs) for all PLC Machines, run the protocols in at least one of the machines, wrote and execute the SVP for in-line printing systems. FMEA analysis to meet FDA 21 CFR part 11 requirements.

1997-12 - **Test Engineer** - NOKIA (formally DSC Communications), Heredia, Costa Rica

DSC Communications established its manufacturing plant in Costa Rica. DSC manufactured a Digital Loop Carrier that Multiplex the last mile copper lines from phones to fiber optic up to the Telephone Carrier Central Office

The technologies used in Manufacturing by DSC Communications were high-tech and the first time they were used in Costa Rica.

The technologies implemented by DSC were:

- Cyber Optics solder paste intelligent machine for SMT
- Fuji America Corporation pick and place SMT machines for small and large components
- Convection Ovens for Solder Mount Technology (SMT) soldering
- Wave Solder machine
- In-circuit test Teradyne machines
- F&G functional testing machines
- Burn-In testing -40 Celsius and +60 Celsius
- ESD proof flooring
- Lean and Six Sigma processes

<u>Achievements</u>: ICT (first past yield, FPY 98%), Functional (FPY 99%), Burn-In (FPY100%), Calibrations, ESD Control, Component Engineer. Part of the start-up engineering staff.